<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Devops on Jesse Builds Software</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/devops/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Devops on Jesse Builds Software</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-CA</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 15:35:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/devops/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The True Cost of Dependencies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-03-27-the-true-cost-of-dependencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 15:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-03-27-the-true-cost-of-dependencies/</guid>
      <description>I used to use Getform for a contact form on my consulting company website. I recently received an email from them announcing that their free tier was dropping from 50 submissions per month to a lifetime limit of 25. This makes it useless for anything more than a trial, and their lowest tier is a more expensive than other similar options.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m not here to complain about companies taking back free offerings.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automating Non-Non-Downtime Upgrades in Kubernetes with ArgoCD</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-06-26-automating-non-non-downtime-upgrades-in-kubernetes-with-argocd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2023 10:55:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-06-26-automating-non-non-downtime-upgrades-in-kubernetes-with-argocd/</guid>
      <description>I recently worked on a project to move a complicated legacy application onto Kubernetes. It was quite an undertaking, but in the end we were successful. One of the biggest challenges was figuring out how to automate our legacy deployment process, one where the whole application has to be stopped completely for schema upgrades to run.&#xA;The normal &amp;ldquo;Kubernetes way&amp;rdquo; to upgrade an application is by changing the Deployment resource. With its default RollingUpdate strategy it will delete a pod with the old definition, start a pod with the new definition, wait for it to be healthy, then repeat continuously until the change is fully applied.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reading Server Graphs: Connected Users</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2013/06/reading-server-graphs-connected-users/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2013 22:30:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2013/06/reading-server-graphs-connected-users/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve spent the last several years working on multi-user server systems in two different companies. Both those companies had a giant monitor hanging off a wall showing a graph of connected users. It won&amp;rsquo;t give you detailed diagnostic information, but it is a good indicator for the health of your servers, and your product generally. If you learn to notice certain patterns in your user graph, it can also save you precious time when things go wrong.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InstallUtil and BadImageFormatException - Facepalm</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2012/04/installutil-and-badimageformatexception/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Apr 2012 23:09:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2012/04/installutil-and-badimageformatexception/</guid>
      <description>I had a frustrating issue at work this week: one that was easy to fix, but embarrassingly difficult to find. I came pretty close to giving up, which is not a solution I often explore, but in the end we figured it out and got everything working.&#xA;A member of our operations team was installing a Windows service I&amp;rsquo;d built to monitor some stuff in our production environment. I&amp;rsquo;ve made a few windows services in my day, and installed them many times on many machines.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Working Together and Having Fun</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2011/01/working-together-and-having-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2011 11:46:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2011/01/working-together-and-having-fun/</guid>
      <description>We did one of our monthly releases at work this week. Releases can be stressful and frustrating, and take a lot of methodical preparation to get right. It can be thankless work too; the only time a user notices a release is when it goes badly. We do our releases early on a week day to minimize impact, so if anything does go wrong, there&amp;rsquo;s not many bodies around to help out.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teaching IT</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2010/12/teaching-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2010 22:28:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2010/12/teaching-it/</guid>
      <description>My company runs a 24/7 site with a substantial number of users and connections to partner systems all over the world. We do what we can to make the system fault tolerant, but problems can still appear at any time of day or night. Ideally we would have a technical support team that&amp;rsquo;s staffed around the clock, but that not in the cards for now.&#xA;We used to have a system where anyone that could fix a problem would get a text message, and whoever was closest to a computer would respond.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>64-bit IIS vs. 32-bit Assemblies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2010/11/64-bit-iis-vs-32-bit-assemblies/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2010 16:45:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2010/11/64-bit-iis-vs-32-bit-assemblies/</guid>
      <description>I found my first 64-bit bug at work. I was moving a windows service built for the &amp;lsquo;Any CPU&amp;rsquo; to a 64-bit server. It started fine on the new server, and gave no indication of poor health in the logs, but one key function was malfunctioning. I&amp;rsquo;m not exactly sure what the cause is, but I know that the hash of any binary file was resulting in the same value. The service does some direct memory manipulation which is a likely culprit.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IE9 Try and Fail</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2010/09/ie9-try-and-fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2010 20:07:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2010/09/ie9-try-and-fail/</guid>
      <description>I decided to give IE9 a try. What&amp;rsquo;s not to like about a browser that&amp;rsquo;s supposed to be faster, cleaner, and support new HTML features?&#xA;They really nailed the faster and cleaner parts. I didn&amp;rsquo;t find the user interface in IE8 too busy, but seeing the improvement I&amp;rsquo;m happy for the extra space.&#xA;Plunking a site onto my task bar like it were an application is pretty awesome. There are a couple of websites that I&amp;rsquo;ll do this for without hesitation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SQL Management Studio Express with VS 2010 Express</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2010/08/ssmse-with-vs2010-express/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 20:16:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2010/08/ssmse-with-vs2010-express/</guid>
      <description>I had some fun trying to install SQL Management Studio on my home computer over the weekend. I was successful in the end, but it was a rough journey.&#xA;These seem to be the things that can lead you into my scenario:&#xA;Windows 7 Visual Web Developer 2010 Express (which installs SQL Server 2008 Express) These are the things I ran into trying to install SQL Management Studio (both from an SQL 2008 standard disk, and a download of the express version from the Microsoft web site):</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
