<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Architecture on Jesse Builds Software</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/architecture/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Architecture on Jesse Builds Software</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-CA</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 12:02:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Pragmatic Potato Tech Stack</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-06-24-pragmatic-potato-tech-stack/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 12:02:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-06-24-pragmatic-potato-tech-stack/</guid>
      <description>I recently launched my new company, Pragmatic Potato Software Inc. The creation of a company itself is pretty easy, but setting up everything you need to do business can become overwhelming quickly. There are a lot of compelling options available, each promising the moon. It&amp;rsquo;s not that simple though.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m going to be writing about the technology stack I&amp;rsquo;m using to run my company, and why I made the choices I did.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Cutting Concerns - Ten Approaches</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-05-27-cross-cutting-concerns/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 13:18:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-05-27-cross-cutting-concerns/</guid>
      <description>One often (and ironically) repeated rule in programming is: don&amp;rsquo;t repeat yourself. We repeat it so much we even have an abbreviation: DRY. There are good reasons for this advice. Duplicating and modifying code can be a quick and easy way to get a feature done, but it can also lead to problems over time. It&amp;rsquo;s harder to understand code when the valuable logic is mixed with reams of low-value boilerplate.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The True Cost of Dependencies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-03-27-the-true-cost-of-dependencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 15:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-03-27-the-true-cost-of-dependencies/</guid>
      <description>I used to use Getform for a contact form on my consulting company website. I recently received an email from them announcing that their free tier was dropping from 50 submissions per month to a lifetime limit of 25. This makes it useless for anything more than a trial, and their lowest tier is a more expensive than other similar options.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m not here to complain about companies taking back free offerings.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Architectural Decision Records</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-11-21-using-architectural-decision-records/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 17:51:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-11-21-using-architectural-decision-records/</guid>
      <description>Architectural Decision Records are a simple technique that promotes good architectural thinking and better collaboration. They don&amp;rsquo;t need to be big or complicated to be effective, but they do take some time, and are yet another step between setting goals and delivering value. If you use them in the right circumstances they can be a big help.&#xA;What is an Architectural Decision Record? An Architectural Decision Record (often abbreviated ADR) is just as the name implies: a document that describes an architectural decision.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This Blog: Hexo-generated static site hosted on GitHub Pages</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-11-01-this-blog-hexo-generated-static-site-hosted-on-github-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 10:34:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-11-01-this-blog-hexo-generated-static-site-hosted-on-github-pages/</guid>
      <description>A couple of years ago I switched this blog from a WordPress site hosted on GoDaddy to a statically generated site. The new setup is faster, more secure, and cheaper to operate. And it was easy to do!&#xA;Static vs Dynamic websites WordPress is a very popular blogging platform. You can use it hosted on WordPress.com, or any number of other web providers that offer it. Because it&amp;rsquo;s open source, you can also host it yourself easily.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regarding Test Coverage Targets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-08-21-regarding-test-coverage-targets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 11:28:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-08-21-regarding-test-coverage-targets/</guid>
      <description>Unit tests are undeniably a good thing, but you only realize the full benefits of them when you have enough tests that you can make changes with confidence. If you can make a change, run your tests, and be comfortable enough to ship your changes, then you and your team can get work done much faster. More drastic changes to the shared code become feasible. Life gets better.&#xA;It makes sense then that teams want to ensure that code is sufficiently covered with tests.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Architectural Report Template</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-08-08-my-architectural-report-template/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2023 12:45:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-08-08-my-architectural-report-template/</guid>
      <description>As an architect I&amp;rsquo;ve been asked to answer a lot of hard questions. I used to waste time figuring out how to structure my answers, preventing me from getting into a good flow sooner. Now I have a simple template that is easy to use, easy to read, and saves me that wasted time up front.&#xA;This template works for simple reports that are only a couple of pages, but can easily be adjusted or expanded for more complicated or much larger documents.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Horizontal One-on-Ones and Talking Practice</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-07-18-horizontal-one-on-ones-and-talking-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 15:35:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-07-18-horizontal-one-on-ones-and-talking-practice/</guid>
      <description>When I was promoted to the role of architect it was a new role in the organization. The stakeholders I had to work with were not used to talking to an architect, and weren&amp;rsquo;t sure what I did or when I should be involved in a conversation. I started using recurring one-on-one meetings with each stakeholder separately. It worked great. It&amp;rsquo;s also made me a much better communicator.&#xA;One of the first and most important lessons I learned as an architect is that you can&amp;rsquo;t design a good architecture without a good understanding of its requirements.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
