<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>War Stories on Jesse Builds Software</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/war-stories/</link>
    <description>Recent content in War Stories on Jesse Builds Software</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-CA</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 15:08:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/war-stories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Case of the Slow Matchmaking Routine</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-09-05-case-of-the-slow-matchmaking-routine/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 15:08:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-09-05-case-of-the-slow-matchmaking-routine/</guid>
      <description>The most challenging bug I&amp;rsquo;ve ever fixed was a performance issue in a matchmaking routine. Matchmaking is the process of finding players to compete against each other in a video game. An excellent matchmaking algorithm doesn&amp;rsquo;t just stick players together randomly; it tries to make the game more fun by balancing power levels and preventing anyone from waiting too long for a match.&#xA;About six weeks before a game I was working on was scheduled to be feature complete, we discovered our routine couldn&amp;rsquo;t handle our load targets.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Case of the Appearing Users</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-07-10-case-of-the-appearing-users/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 13:18:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-07-10-case-of-the-appearing-users/</guid>
      <description>A couple of years after solving The Case of The Disappearing Users, I was assigned another high profile bug where new users were being spontaneously created. They were being generated without a name or any profile information, but still filling up space in lists and appearing on schedules. A couple of other developers had tried fixing it but had no luck, so it was assigned to me.&#xA;I went through my usual bag of tricks: searched recent changes, searched for insert statements, tried to create empty users manually (and couldn&amp;rsquo;t).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Case of the Disappearing Users</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-05-01-case-of-the-disappearing-users/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 08:26:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-05-01-case-of-the-disappearing-users/</guid>
      <description>Many years ago I worked on a program that had a serious problem: the users in one customer&amp;rsquo;s system were getting deleted periodically. When a user was deleted, any data linked with them was also deleted. We could restore the data from backups, but it was a difficult process, and having a system that loses data wasn&amp;rsquo;t great for our reputation, so we wanted to resolve it quickly. Our VP of development tried to find the issue first, but after a day without any progress he assigned the issue to me.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
