<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogging on Jesse Builds Software</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/blogging/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogging on Jesse Builds Software</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-CA</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 10:34:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/blogging/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>This Blog: Hexo-generated static site hosted on GitHub Pages</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-11-01-this-blog-hexo-generated-static-site-hosted-on-github-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 10:34:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-11-01-this-blog-hexo-generated-static-site-hosted-on-github-pages/</guid>
      <description>A couple of years ago I switched this blog from a WordPress site hosted on GoDaddy to a statically generated site. The new setup is faster, more secure, and cheaper to operate. And it was easy to do!&#xA;Static vs Dynamic websites WordPress is a very popular blogging platform. You can use it hosted on WordPress.com, or any number of other web providers that offer it. Because it&amp;rsquo;s open source, you can also host it yourself easily.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review: Grammarly Premium</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-10-19-review-grammarly-premium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2023 08:50:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-10-19-review-grammarly-premium/</guid>
      <description>I spend a fair bit of time working on this blog. More than I probably should given my unimpressive view metrics. It does help me to crystalize my thoughts and practice articulating points that are important to me, but I&amp;rsquo;m spending an awful lot of time doing it. Ultimately, I write because I enjoy writing. I just wish I could spend less time per post.&#xA;For a while there I was getting hammered by ads from Grammarly, and in a fit of frustration, or maybe I was avoiding yet another hour of editing, I signed up.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My First Open Source Project</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2010/09/my-first-open-source-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2010 19:52:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2010/09/my-first-open-source-project/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending time on the first part of the shared resource service project: &amp;ldquo;Receive event invitations by email and send an acceptance email&amp;rdquo;. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t considered the difficulty I would face receiving emails. This is the most important part of the application, and if I can&amp;rsquo;t make it work, there&amp;rsquo;s really no point to continue.&#xA;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to write my own POP3 library, I&amp;rsquo;ve done that before and it&amp;rsquo;s much more complicated than it appears.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My First Post</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2010/07/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2010 22:22:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2010/07/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve finally gone and done it.&#xA;To be honest, creating my own blog wasn&amp;rsquo;t foremost in my thoughts until fairly recently. Scott Hanselman had a couple of interesting videos on his blog that finally convinced me to do it.&#xA;I hope you like it.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
